Finding aid to the Harriet Boyd Hawes Papers CA.MS.00102
Smith College Archives
Harriet Boyd Hawes Papers
1874-1967
Smith College Archives
Hawes, Harriet Boyd, 1871-1945.
CA.MS.00102
4.833 linear feet (13 containers)
Instructor of Greek, archaeologist, nurse, relief worker. Contains writings, correspondence, journals, news clippings, notes, photographs, and publications.
Biographical / Historical
Harriet Boyd Hawes was born on October 11, 1871 in Boston, Massachusetts. She was educated at the Prospect Hill School in Greenfield and graduated from Smith College in 1892 with a degree in classics. Hawes always felt a deep love for Greece and a strong desire to understand its culture and history. She studied at the American School at Athens from 1896-97 and the next year became a Fellow there. While in Greece, she learned that the Greeks (who were in the midst of the first Greco-Turkish War) had no nursing supplies and with support from the Queen of Greece soon became a nursing volunteer. Several years later she was decorated by the Queen for her contributions.
Hawes soon became well known not only for her volunteer work but also for her expertise in the field of archaeology. For four months in the spring of 1900, she led an excavation at Kavousi, Crete during which she discovered houses and tombs from the Geometric period (900 BC). During another excavation less than a year later in Gournia, Crete, she discovered a Mycenaean provincial town and later published a book entitled, Crete: the Forerunner of Greece.
Hawes accepted a position at Smith College teaching Greek archaeology in 1900 and received her M.A. from Smith in 1901. She taught at Smith until 1905 interspersing her time there with frequent trips abroad for archaeological excursions. During one trip to Crete, she met Charles Henry Hawes, an English anthropologist and archeologist who later became the associate director of the Boston Museum of Fine Arts. They were married on March 3, 1906 and nine months later their son, Alexander Boyd Hawes was born. A daughter, Mary Nesbit Hawes followed in August of 1910. By this time Charles was teaching at Dartmouth and the family was living in Hanover, New Hampshire.
Despite her commitment to her family, Hawes remained active in both humanities and her field of archaeology. In 1910, Hawes received an honorary degree from Smith College. She traveled to Corfu in 1915 for a year to work extensively with the Serbian Army. In 1916, she helped the wounded in France and a year later she founded and was the first director of the Smith College Relief Unit in France. She held this title for three years during which time she worked as a nurse's aide at the YMCA.
In 1920, the Hawes' moved to Cambridge and Harriet joined the faculty at Wellesley lecturing on Ancient Art. When Charles retired in 1936, the couple moved to Washington D.C. where Harriet remained after her husband died. She died on March 31, 1945.
Biographical / Historical
1871 Born Boston, Massachusetts, October 11
1892-96 Teacher of Classics, schools in North Carolina and Delaware
1892 Graduated from Smith College
1896 Graduate work, American School of Classical Studies, Athens
1897 Nurse and relief worker in Thessaly with Greek Army, Greco-Turkish War
1898-99 Fellow of American School of Classical Studies, Athens
1898 Nurse Spanish-American War in Tampa, Florida - Summer
1899-00 Agnes Hoppin Memorial Fellow, Bryn Mawr College
1900 Excavation at Kavousi, Crete - May-June
1900-06 Part-time Instructor, Smith College in Archaeology, Epigraphy and modern Greek
1901-04 Director of excavations of the American Exploration Society - Gournia, Crete, Assisted by Blanche Emily Wheeler 1892.
1901 M.A. Smith College
1902 First woman invited to address the Societies of the Archaeological Institute of American
1906 Married Charles Henry Hawes
1910 Awarded Doctor of Humane Letters, Smith College
1915-16 Established hospital for wounded and ill on Corfu for Serbian army - World War I
1917-18 Organizer and first Director of Smith College Relief Unit in France - World War I
1918-20 Nurse's aid with YMCA at American Hospital, Longchamps - World War I
1920-36 Lecturer in Ancient Art, Wellesley College
1933 Sued by A.R. Hyde and Son, for damages resulting from her involvement in company strike
1938 Traveled to Czechoslovakia during take-over of Sudetenland, detained by German authorities
1945 Died March 31, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Contents
The Harriet Boyd Hawes Papers document her work as an archaeologist and as a nurse and relief worker in three wars. They contain a large amount of writings, both published and unpublished, on various subjects relating to her professional work and volunteer activities as well as her political opinions. There is personal, and professional correspondence dating from 1886-1945 and a small amount of material on her career as a college instructor at Smith and Wellesley Colleges.
The material is arranged in five series: Biographical Material, Correspondence, Professional Life, Publications and Activities. Where appropriate, correspondence and publications may have been placed under one of the other headings.
The material relating to Hawes' professional life documents her excavations on Crete (1900-04) and contains correspondence, journals, news clippings, some notes on excavations and photographs of sites, objects and graves. Included are photographs of objects that are housed in the University Museum at the University of Pennsylvania in Philadelphia.
Publications include drafts of published and unpublished books and articles on ancient art and on her field work, plus one short story and scenarios intended for films.
Hawes' work as a nurse and relief worker in the Greco-Turkish War in 1897 is documented in detail. There are drafts of her manuscripts In Defense of Crete (1914) and Greek Cross and Red Cross (1898?) plus news articles, clippings and some photographs. Her World War I activities are documented in various accounts of her experiences as a representative of the American Distributing Service on Corfu where she organized a hospital for the wounded and ill of the Serbian Army (1915-16). There are approximately 30 photographs of the facility, its staff and surroundings. Hawes' work with the Smith College Relief Unit (1917-18) is documented by correspondence and writings on the founding of the Unit, plus a journal, news clippings and photographs.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into five series:
I. Biographical Material
II. Correspondence
III. Professional Life
IV. Publications
V. Activities
Related Material
12. Smith College Relief Unit
12. Symposium: Land Called Crete, 1967
University Museum at the University of Pennsylvania
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers of Harriet Boyd Hawes were given to Smith College by her daughter, Mrs. Mary Nesbit Allsebrook in 1967. Additional material was received in 1982 from Phyllis Lehmann, a student of Hawes and Professor Emeritus of Art at Smith College.
Archaeologists--United States.; Women archaeologists--United States.; Hawes, Harriet Boyd, 1871-1945.; Smith College--Faculty.
- Series I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL
  - Contents of Collection (Box 851, Folder 1)
  - Autobiography "Memories and Opinions", 1944 (Box 851, Folder 2)
  - Notes and drafts (Box 851, Folder 3)
  - Award, L.H.D. Smith College, 1910 (Box 851, Folder 4)
  - General and miscellaneous (Box 851, Folder 5)
  - Education, Prospect Hill School, 1888 (Box 851, Folder 6)
  - Education, Smith College, 1888-92 (Box 851, Folder 7)
  - Family miscellaneous (Box 851, Folder 8)
  - Family photographs (Box 851, Folder 9)
  - Fellowship, American School of Classical Studies, Athens, 1898-99 (Box 851, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1896-99 (Box 851, Folder 11)
    - Photographs (Box 851, Folder 12)
  - Fellowship, Archaeological Institute of America, 1902 (Box 851, Folder 13)
  - Journal, religious (1892), Line-A-Day (1896-1900) (Box 851, Folder 14)
    - printed material from Hull House, 1902-04 (Box 851, Folder 15)
    - Line-A-Day, 1901-05 (Box 851, Folder 16)
    - Xerox copy (Box 851, Folder 17)
    - 1908-1917 (Box 854, Folder 18)
    - 1918-24 (Box 854, Folder 19)
    - 1931 (Box 854, Folder 20)
  - "Miss Boyd - A Rebel from Boston" unpublished, biography by Mary Nesbit Allsebrook, 1967 (Box 855)
  - Photographs, 1874-1962 (Box 856, Folder 21)
  - Poetry (Box 856, Folder 22)
  - Religion (Box 856, Folder 23)
  - Symposium at Smith College, A Land Called Crete, 1967 (Box 856, Folder 24)
  - Trip to Prague - Account by H.B.H., 1938 (Box 856, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence, Misc., 1938 (Box 856, Folder 26)
- Series II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - From:
    - Boyd, Alexander (brother), 1890-91 (Box 856, Folder 27)
    - Boyd, Allen (brother), 1910 (Box 856, Folder 28)
    - MacKenzie, Duncan, 1910 (Box 856, Folder 29)
    - Olga, Queen of Greece, 1912-20 (Box 856, Folder 30)
      - photographs (Box 856, Folder 31)
    - Richter, Gisela, 1906 (Box 856, Folder 32)
    - Ridgeway, William, 1909 (Box 856, Folder 33)
    - Santayana, George (Box 856, Folder 34)
    - Tyler, Henry M. President Seelye, 1908-14 (Box 856, Folder 35)
  - To:
    - Allesbrook, Mary (daughter), 1921-1939 (Box 856, Folder 36)
    - Allesbrook Mary (daughter), 1940-44 (Box 856, Folder 37)
    - Averny, Myrtilla, 1934 (Box 856, Folder 38)
    - Boyd, Alex and Ida (cousins), 1905-13 (Box 856, Folder 39)
    - Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1939-41 (Box 856, Folder 40)
    - Roosevelt, Franklin Delano, 1937-45 (Box 856, Folder 41)
    - Swing, Raymond Gram, 1942-43 (Box 856, Folder 42)
    - Waring, Mary Kimberly, 1899-1945 (Box 856, Folder 43)
      - Photographs (Box 856, Folder 44)
    - Miscellaneous, 1888; 1892 (Box 856, Folder 45)
    - Miscellaneous, 1916-19 (Box 856, Folder 46)
    - Miscellaneous, 1920-23 (Box 856, Folder 47)
    - Miscellaneous, 1924-30 (Box 856, Folder 48)
    - Miscellaneous, 1931-34 (Box 856, Folder 49)
    - Miscellaneous, 1935-37 (Box 856, Folder 50)
    - Miscellaneous, 1938-39 (Box 856, Folder 51)
    - Miscellaneous, 1940 (Box 856, Folder 52)
    - Miscellaneous, 1941-42 (Box 856, Folder 53)
    - Miscellaneous, 1943-45 (Box 856, Folder 54)
    - Waring, Mary Kimberly from:Sarah Storer, 1892-1894 (Box 856, Folder 55)
      - Miscellaneous, 1894-1905 (Box 856, Folder 56)
      - Wheeler, Blanche Emily, 1900-01 (Box 856, Folder 57)
- Series III. PROFESSIONAL LIFE
  - Lectures: advertisements, correspondence, 1901-14 (Box 857, Folder 58)
  - News clippings, 1901-14 (Box 857, Folder 59)
  - Kavousi
    - Correspondence, May-Jun 1900 (Box 857, Folder 60)
    - News Clippings (Box 857, Folder 61)
    - Notes (Box 857, Folder 62)
    - Publications, 1901-03 (Box 857, Folder 63)
  - Gournia
    - Correspondence, 1901-05 (Box 857, Folder 64)
    - Journal (Mar-Ap), 1901 (Box 857, Folder 65)
    - Journal (May), 1901 (Box 857, Folder 66)
    - Journal of trip (Feb-Mar), 1904 (Box 857, Folder 67)
    - Journal (Ap-Jul), 1904 (Box 857, Folder 68)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 857, Folder 69)
    - Notes (Box 857, Folder 70)
  - Crete - Correspondence and Notes, 1926 (Box 857, Folder 71)
  - Photographs
    - Graves (Box 857, Folder 72)
    - Kavousi (Box 857, Folder 73)
    - miscellaneous (Box 857, Folder 74)
    - pottery (Box 857, Folder 75-76)
    - site (Box 857, Folder 77)
    - site and landscape (Box 857, Folder 78)
  - Speeches, 1916-17 (Box 858, Folder 79)
  - Speech at Alumnae Assembly, Jun 18, 1912 (Box 858, Folder 80)
  - Speeches, Balkan War, 1912 (Box 858, Folder 81)
  - Wellesley College Syllabi (Box 858, Folder 82)
- Series IV. PUBLICATIONS
  - "Amalasuntha" (scenario), 1938-39 (Box 859, Folder 83)
  - Christianity and Hellanism, 1924? (Box 859, Folder 84)
  - Crete the Forerunner of Greece with Charles Henry Hawes, 1909 (Box 859, Folder 85, Box 854.1)
    - Correspondence, 1909-10 (Box 859, Folder 86)
  - "A Cretan Pompeii", 1901 (Box 859, Folder 87)
  - "The First International Congress of Archaeology", 1905 (Box 859, Folder 88)
  - Five Riddles of Greek Art
    - Chapter 1, outline, undated (Box 859, Folder 89)
    - Chapter 3, undated (Box 859, Folder 90)
    - Chapter 4, undated (Box 859, Folder 91)
    - Chapter 5, undated (Box 859, Folder 92)
    - Illustrations, undated (Box 859, Folder 93)
    - Chapter 6, undated (Box 859, Folder 94)
    - Illustrations, undated (Box 859, Folder 95)
    - Chapter 7, undated (Box 859, Folder 96)
  - "The General Election in England", 1910 (Box 859, Folder 97)
  - "A Gift of Themistocles: The Ludovisi Throne and the Boston Relief", 1921 (Box 859, Folder 98)
  - Gournia manuscript, 1905 (Box 859, Folder 99-100)
  - Gournia, Vasiliki and other Prehistoric sites on the Isthmus of Hierapetr a - manuscript, 1908 (Box 859, Folder 101)
    - Correspondence, news clippings and advertisement, 1907-15 (Box 859, Folder 102)
    - Gournia miscellaneous, undated (Box 859, Folder 103)
  - "Greece and Archaeology", undated (Box 859, Folder 104)
  - "An Immediate Appeal to America by the People of Greece", 1919 (Box 859, Folder 105)
  - "Ivanhoe" (scenario), 1924 (Box 859, Folder 106)
  - "Larger Loyalties", undated (Box 859, Folder 107)
  - "Memoirs of a Pioneer Excavator in Crete"
    - Part I, 1965 (Box 864, Folder 108)
    - Part II, 1965 (Box 864, Folder 109)
  - "The Minotaur and the Maiden" (scenario), 1927? (Box 864, Folder 110)
  - "Prince George and Venizelos in Crete", 1906 (Box 864, Folder 111)
  - "The Quest of a Buried City", 1913 (Box 864, Folder 112)
  - "The Smith College Relief Unit", 1917 (Box 864, Folder 113)
  - "Theseus, Prince of Athens" (scenario), undated (Box 864, Folder 114)
  - War experiences, outline and draft for article 1906 (Box 864, Folder 115)
  - "When the Mummy Moves", 1937 (Box 864, Folder 116)
    - Contest, 1907-08 (Box 864, Folder 117)
    - Correspondence, 1935-37 (Box 864, Folder 118)
- Series V. ACTIVITIES
  - Goldsborough Bills, 1934-37 (Box 861, Folder 119)
  - Goldsborough Bills, 1938-39 (Box 861, Folder 120)
  - Hyde Company Strike, 1933 (Box 861, Folder 121)
  - Hyde Company Strike, Correspondence (Box 861, Folder 122)
  - Political Opinions (Box 861, Folder 123)
  - War work - Greco-Turkish War
    - Correspondence, Feb-Mar; 1897 (Box 861, Folder 124)
    - Correspondence, Apr-May; 1897 (Box 861, Folder 125)
    - Correspondence, Jun-Aug; 1897 (Box 861, Folder 126)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 861, Folder 127)
    - Miscellaneous writings (Box 861, Folder 128)
    - News articles and clippings (Box 861, Folder 129)
    - Photographs (Box 861, Folder 130)
    - Greek Cross and Red Cross, Ch. 1, 1898? (Box 861, Folder 131)
      - Chapter 2 (Box 861, Folder 132)
      - Chapter 3 (Box 861, Folder 133)
      - Chapter 4 (Box 861, Folder 134)
      - Chapter 5 (Box 861, Folder 135)
      - Chapter 6 (Box 861, Folder 136)
      - Chapter 7 (Box 861, Folder 137)
      - Chapter 8 (Box 861, Folder 138)
      - Chapter 9 (Box 861, Folder 139)
  - "Nursing with the Greek Army in 1897" (Box 861, Folder 140)
    General
    ****See also oversize box for In Defense of Crete
  - Spanish - American War, 1898 (Box 862, Folder 141)
  - World War I, Corfu - Correspondence 1915- 1916 (Box 862, Folder 142)
    - Correspondence, (Mar-Ap) 1916 (Box 862, Folder 143)
    - News clippings, 1915-1916 (Box 862, Folder 144)
    - Photographs, 1916 (Box 862, Folder 145)
    - miscellaneous (Box 862, Folder 146)
    - Records and documents (Box 862, Folder 147)
    - Speeches and writings (Box 862, Folder 148)
  - World War I, Smith College Relief Unit - Correspondence, May 1917 (Box 862, Folder 149)
    - Correspondence, Jun 1917 (Box 862, Folder 150)
    - Correspondence, Jul-Aug 1917 (Box 862, Folder 151)
    - Correspondence, Sep-Oct 1917 (Box 862, Folder 152)
    - Correspondence, Nov-Dec 1917 (Box 862, Folder 153)
    - Correspondence, 1918 (Box 862, Folder 154)
    - Correspondence, 1919-29; undated (Box 862, Folder 155)
    - Pub. "The Gates of Grecourt", 1924 (Box 862, Folder 156)
    - General and miscellaneous (Box 862, Folder 157)
      - Journal, 1917-18 (Box 862, Folder 158)
      - News clippings (Box 862, Folder 159)
      - Photographs (Box 862, Folder 160)
  - World War I, Smith College Relief Unit - Confidential (Box 862, Folder 161)
  - Oversize: War Work - Greco-Turkish War, 1897, includes manuscript In Defense of Crete. (Box 864.1)
- Addition (1994) (Box 860.1)